So, stepping down out of the bus,
إذا , وأنا أترجل من الحافلة
I headed back to the corner
اتجهت إلى الزاوية
to head west en route to a braille training session.
لأتجه غرباً إلى مركز التدريب على لغة بريل .
It was the winter of 2009,
كان وقتها خريف عام 2009
and I had been blind for about a year.
وقد مضت سنةٌ على فقداني للبصر .
Things were going pretty well.
وكانت الأمور تسير بشكل جيد .
Safely reaching the other side,
وصلت بأمان إلى الطرف الآخر .
I turned to the left,
التفت إلى اليسار
pushed the auto-button for the audible pedestrian signal,
وضغطت على زر السيارات لإشارة المرور الصوتية
and waited my turn.
وانتظرت دوري .
As it went off, I took off
وعندما توقف الصوت , انطلقت
and safely got to the other side.
ووصلت بأمان إلى الجانب الآخر .
Stepping onto the sidewalk,
خطوت على الرصيف
I then heard the sound of a steel chair
عندها سمعت صوت كرسي معدني
slide across the concrete sidewalk in front of me.
ينزلق عبر الرصيف الإسمنتي ليقف في وجهي .
I know there's a cafe on the corner,
كنت أعرف بوجود مقهى عند تلك الزاوية
and they have chairs out in front,
ولديهم بمقدمة المقهى كراسي
so I just adjusted to the left
لذا عدلت سيري إلى اليسار
to get closer to the street.
لأقترب من الشارع .
As I did, so slid the chair.
وعندما فعلت ذلك , فعل الكرسي الشيء نفسه .
I just figured I'd made a mistake,
اكتشفت أنني أخطأت ,
and went back to the right,
فعدت إلى اليمين
and so slid the chair in perfect synchronicity.
وعاد معي الكرسي بتناغم ممتاز .
Now I was getting a little anxious.
الآن بدأت أشعر بالقلق .
I went back to the left,
عدت إلى اليسار
and so slid the chair,
وكذلك عاد الكرسي معي
blocking my path of travel.
ليمنعني من المرور .
Now, I was officially freaking out.
الآن أصبت رسمياً بالهلع .
So I yelled,
لذا صرخت
"Who the hell's out there? What's going on?"
"من هناك ؟ ماذا يحدث ؟"
Just then, over my shout,
وفي تلك اللحظة أثناء صراخي
I heard something else, a familiar rattle.
سمعت شيئاً آخر , حشرجة مألوفة .
It sounded familiar,
بدت مألوفة
and I quickly considered another possibility,
وفوراً افترضت احتمالاً آخر
and I reached out with my left hand,
ومددت يدي اليسرى
as my fingers brushed against something fuzzy,
ودخلت أصابعي بشيء زَغِبْ
and I came across an ear,
ولامست أُذناً
the ear of a dog, perhaps a golden retriever.
أذن كلب , ربما من نوع ريتريفر ذهبي
Its leash had been tied to the chair
وكان طوقه مربوطاً للكرسي
as her master went in for coffee,
لأن صاحبها دخل ليشتري القهوة
and she was just persistent in her efforts
وكانت مصممة بجهودها
to greet me, perhaps get a scratch behind the ear.
على تحيتي , وربما أن تحصل على حكة خلف أذنها .
Who knows, maybe she was volunteering for service.
من يدري , ربما كانت تطوع للخدمة .
(Laughter)
(صوت ضحك)
But that little story is really about
لكن تلك القصة هي في الحقيقة عن
the fears and misconceptions that come along
الخوف من سوء الفهم الذي يأتي مع
with the idea of moving through the city
فكرة التنقل في المدينة
without sight,
بدون بصر
seemingly oblivious to the environment
غافلٌ بشكل ظاهري عن البيئة
and the people around you.
والناس المحيطين بك .
So let me step back and set the stage a little bit.
لذا دعوني أعود لأمهد الطريق قليلاً .
On St. Patrick's Day of 2008,
في يوم القديس باترييك في عام 2008
I reported to the hospital for surgery
نقلت إلى المشفى لإجراء عملية
to remove a brain tumor.
لاستئصال ورم دماغي .
The surgery was successful.
كانت العملية ناجحة .
Two days later, my sight started to fail.
وبعد يومين ، بدأ بصري يضعف .
On the third day, it was gone.
وفي اليوم الثالث ، توقف تماماً .
Immediately, I was struck by an incredible sense
في تلك اللحظة بالضبط , خالجني شعور رهيب
of fear, of confusion, of vulnerability,
بالخوف ، والارتباك ، والضعف
like anybody would.
كأي أحد فقد بصره .
But as I had time to stop and think,
ولكن وبعد أن توافر لي الوقت لأفكر
I actually started to realize
بدأت ألاحظ
I had a lot to be grateful for.
أن لدي الكثير لأكون شاكراً عليه .
In particular, I thought about my dad,
بالتحديد ، فكرت بوالدي
who had passed away from complications
الذي توفي جراء مضاعفات
from brain surgery.
عمل جراحي للدماغ .
He was 36. I was seven at the time.
كان في السادسة والثلاثين من عمره , وأنا كنت في السابعة .
So although I had every reason
لذا وعلى الرغم من أنه لدي الحق
to be fearful of what was ahead,
بأن أخاف من القادم
and had no clue quite what was going to happen,
وعلى الرغم من عدم معرفتي لأي شيء عما سيحصل
I was alive.
لقد كنت حياً .
My son still had his dad.
وابني لا يزال لديه والده .
And besides, it's not like I was the first person
وإلى جانب ذلك , لست أول شخص
ever to lose their sight.
يفقد بصره .
I knew there had to be all sorts of systems
كنت اعرف أن هناك العديد من أنواع الأنظمة
and techniques and training to have
والتقنيات والتدريبات التي علي أن أخوضها
to live a full and meaningful, active life
لأعيش حياة فعالة وذات معنى
without sight.
بدون بصر .
So by the time I was discharged from the hospital
و مع مرور الوقت ، خرجت من المستشفى
a few days later, I left with a mission,
بعد بضعة أيام، غادرت مع بعثة،
a mission to get out and get the best training
بعثة إلى الخروج والحصول على أفضل تدريب
as quickly as I could and get on to rebuilding my life.
بأسرع ما أستطيع و
Within six months, I had returned to work.
في غضون ستة أشهر، عدت إلى العمل.
My training had started.
وحينها بدأ تدريبي
I even started riding a tandem bike
لقد بدأت حتى ركوب دراجة متعددة الراكبين
with my old cycling buddies,
مع رفاقي القدامى راكبي الدراجات
and was commuting to work on my own,
وكنت أتنقل الى مكان العمل على طريقتي،
walking through town and taking the bus.
أمشي خلال المدينة و أركب الحافلة.
It was a lot of hard work.
كان هناك الكثير من العمل الشاق
But what I didn't anticipate
ولكن ما لم أكن أتوقع
through that rapid transition
من خلال هذا التحول السريع
was the incredible experience of the juxtaposition
كانت التجزبة المدهشة من هذا التصادم
of my sighted experience up against my unsighted experience
من تجربتي حالة الابصار مقابل تجربتي بعد فقده
of the same places and the same people
من نفس الأماكن ونفس الأشخاص
within such a short period of time.
خلال فترة قصيرة من الوقت.
From that came a lot of insights,
حصلت خلالهاعلى الكثير من الرؤى
or outsights, as I called them,
أو اللا رؤى، كما أدعوه
things that I learned since losing my sight.
أشياء تعلمتها منذ فقدت الرؤية
These outsights ranged from the trival
هذه الرؤى تراوحت ما بين المتواضعة
to the profound,
الى العميقة
from the mundane to the humorous.
من المملة الى المضحكة
As an architect, that stark juxtaposition
كمهندس معماري، انه تصادم بكل معنى الكلمة
of my sighted and unsighted experience
من تجربتي حال الابصار و بعدها
of the same places and the same cities
من نفس الأماكن ونفس المدن
within such a short period of time
خلال فترة قصيرة من الوقت
has given me all sorts of wonderful outsights
وقد أعطاني جميع أنواع الرؤى الرائعة
of the city itself.
من المدينة نفسها.
Paramount amongst those
الافضل من بين تلك الرؤى الرائعة
was the realization that, actually,
كان ادراك ذلك ، فعلا !
cities are fantastic places for the blind.
المدن أماكن جميلة للمكفوفين
And then I was also surprised
و حينها كنت متفاجئا أيضا
by the city's propensity for kindness and care
ميل سكان المدن للرحمة و العناية
as opposed to indifference or worse.
بدلاً من اللامبالاة أو ما هو أسوأ.
And then I started to realize that
ومن ثم بدأت أدرك بأنه
it seemed like the blind seemed to have
بدا و كأنه المكفوفين بدو يملكون
a positive influence on the city itself.
تأثير إيجابي على المدينة نفسها.
That was a little curious to me.
التي كانت غريبة بعض الشيء بالنسبة لي.
Let me step back and take a look
اسمحوا لي أن أخطو خطوة إلى الوراء و ألقي نظرة
at why the city is so good for the blind.
لماذا المدينة جيدة جدا للمكفوفين!
Inherent with the training for recovery from sight loss
في الوقت الذي تتدرب فيه لاستعادة بصرك
is learning to rely on all your non-visual senses,
تتعلم الاعتماد على جيع حواسك اللابصرية
things that you would otherwise maybe ignore.
أشياء كنت على خلاف ذلك ممكن أن تتجاهلها
It's like a whole new world of sensory information
مثل عالما جديداً من المعلومات الحسية
opens up to you.
تفتح لك
I was really struck by the symphony
لقد صدمني هذا الانسجام
of subtle sounds all around me in the city
من الأصوات الخفية من حولي في المدينة
that you can hear and work with
يمكن أن تسمعها و تتجاوب معها
to understand where you are,
لتعرف أين أنت الآن ،
how you need to move, and where you need to go.
كيف يمكنك أن تتحرك، و أين يمكنك أن تذهب
Similarly, just through the grip of the cane,
وبالمثل، فقط عن طريق القبض على العصا
you can feel contrasting textures in the floor below,
يمكنك الشعور باختلاف البنية من تحتك
and over time you build a pattern of where you are
ومع مرور الوقت يمكنك بناء مخطط لمكان وجودك
and where you're headed.
و أين تتجه
Similarly, just the sun warming one side of your face
وبالمثل، الشمس تدفئ جهة واحدة من وجهك،
or the wind at your neck
الرياح تهب على رقبتك
gives you clues about your alignment
تمنحك أدلة حول محاذاتك
and your progression through a block
وتقدمك خلال عائق
and your movement through time and space.
و حركتك عبر الزمان والمكان.
But also, the sense of smell.
و حاسة الشم أيضا
Some districts and cities have their own smell,
بعض المقاطعات والمدن لها رائحتها المميزة
as do places and things around you,
كما تفعل الأماكن والأشياء من حولك،
and if you're lucky, you can even follow your nose
وإذا كنت محظوظاً، يمكنك أن تتبع أنفك
to that new bakery that you've been looking for.
الى مخبز جديد كنت تبحث عنه
All this really surprised me,
كل هذا حقاً أدهشني !
because I started to realize that
لأنني بدأت أدرك ذلك
my unsighted experienced
خبرتي اللا بصرية
was so far more multi-sensory
كانت حتى الآن أكثر تعددية للحواس
than my sighted experience ever was.
من تجربة الابصار مطلقا
What struck me also was how much the city
ما أدهشني حقا كم كانت المدينة
was changing around me.
كانت تتغير من حولي
When you're sighted,
عندما تبصر
everybody kind of sticks to themselves,
الكل لديه عوائق في نفسه
you mind your own business.
تذكر عملك الخاص
Lose your sight, though,
تفقد بصرك، رغم ذلك،
and it's a whole other story.
و هذه قصة أخرى مختلفة
And I don't know who's watching who,
لا أعرف من يشاهد من
but I have a suspicion that a lot of people are watching me.
ولكن لدى شكوك أن كثير من الناس يراقبوني
And I'm not paranoid, but everywhere I go,
لست كثير الشك، ولكن في كل مكان اذهب إليه
I'm getting all sorts of advice:
أتلقى كل أنواع المشورة:
Go here, move there, watch out for this.
اذهب هنا، تحرك إلى هناك، وانتبه لهذا.
A lot of the information is good.
كثير من المعلومات أمر جيد.
Some of it's helpful. A lot of it's kind of reversed.
البعض منها مفيدة و كثير منها على عكس ذلك
You've got to figure out what they actually meant.
كنت قد عرفت ما كانوا حقا يعنون.
Some of it's kind of wrong and not helpful.
بعض منها خاطئ وليس نافع
But it's all good in the grand scheme of things.
ولكن كل شيء جيد في المخطط الكبير للأشياء.
But one time I was in Oakland
ولكن مرة واحدة عندما كنت في أوكلاند
walking along Broadway, and came to a corner.
امشي على طول برودواي، و جئت إلى زاوية.
I was waiting for an audible pedestrian signal,
كنت في انتظار إشارة المشاة مسموعة،
and as it went off, I was just about to step out into the street,
وعندما توقف الصوت ،كنت على وشك أن أخطو الى الجانب الاخر
when all of a sudden, my right hand
عندما فجأة، يدي اليمنى
was just gripped by this guy,
مسكها هذ الرجل
and he yanked my arm and pulled me out into the crosswalk
و جذب ذراعي ليعبر بي الى الجهة الاخرى من الطريق
and was dragging me out across the street,
و كان يسحبني خلال الطريق
speaking to me in Mandarin.
يتكلم معي بالفصحى
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's like, there was no escape from this man's death grip,
أنها مثل، لا مفر من قبضته المميته
but he got me safely there.
ولكنه عبر بي بسلام
What could I do?
ماذا يمكن أن أفعل..
But believe me, there are more polite ways
صدقوني، هناك طرق أكثر تهذيبا
to offer assistance.
لتقديم المساعدة.
We don't know you're there,
لا نعرف أنك هناك،
so it's kind of nice to say "Hello" first.
انه من الجميل أن تقول "مرحبا"
"Would you like some help?"
"هل تريد بعض المساعدة؟"
But while in Oakland, I've really been struck by
ولكن بينما في أوكلاند، كنت حقا منبهرا
how much the city of Oakland changed
كم كانت المدينة قد تغيرت
as I lost my sight.
كما فقدت البصر
I liked it sighted. It was fine.
لقد أحببتها مبصرة، كانت على مايرام
It's a perfectly great city.
انها حقا مدينة عظيمة بحق
But once I lost my sight
ولكن بمجرد ان فقدت البصر
and was walking along Broadway,
وكنت أسير في برودواي
I was blessed every block of the way.
كنت ابارك كل قطعة في طريقي
"Bless you, man."
"ليبارك لك، رجل."
"Go for it, brother."
"افعلها، أخي."
"God bless you."
"بارك الله لك."
I didn't get that sighted.
لم أحصل على ذلك عندما كنت أبصر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And even without sight, I don't get that in San Francisco.
وحتى بدون البصر، لم احصل على ذلك في سان فرانسيسكو.
And I know it bothers some of my blind friends,
وأنا أعلم أنه يزعج بعض أصدقائي المكفوفين،
it's not just me.
ليس انا فقط
Often it's thought that
غالبا ما يعتقد انها
that's an emotion that comes up out of pity.
عاطفة تأتي بسبب الشفقة
I tend to think that it comes out of our shared humanity,
وإميل إلى الاعتقاد بأن الأمر أتى بسبب إنسانيتنا المشتركة،
out of our togetherness, and I think it's pretty cool.
من وحدتنا، وأعتقد أنه أمر رائع.
In fact, if I'm feeling down,
في الواقع، إذا كنت أشعر بالاحباط
I just go to Broadway in downtown Oakland,
فقط أذهب الى برودواي في وسط مدينة أوكلاند
I go for a walk, and I feel better like that,
اذهب للنزهة، وأشعر حينها بالتحسن
in no time at all.
في أي وقت من الأوقات على الإطلاق.
But also that it illustrates how
ويوضح أيضا كيف أن
disability and blindness
الإعاقة والعمى
sort of cuts across ethnic, social,
نوع من ال عبر العرقية والاجتماعية،
racial, economic lines.
الخطوط العرقية والاقتصادية.
Disability is an equal-opportunity provider.
العجز موفر تكافؤ الفرص.
Everybody's welcome.
الجميع موضع ترحيب.
In fact, I've heard it said in the disability community
وفي الواقع، لقد سمعت أنه قال في المجتمع الإعاقة
that there are really only two types of people:
أن هناك حقاً إلا نوعين من الناس:
There are those with disabilities,
وهناك من ذوي الإعاقة،
and there are those that haven't quite found theirs yet.
وهناك تلك التي لم تكن قد وجدت لهم تماما حتى الآن.
It's a different way of thinking about it,
أنها طريقة مختلفة للتفكير فيه،
but I think it's kind of beautiful,
ولكن أعتقد أنها نوع من الجميل،
because it is certainly far more inclusive
لأنه من المؤكد الآن أكثر شمولاً
than the us-versus-them
من بنا-مقابل-منهم
or the abled-versus-the-disabled,
أو قدراتهم-مقابل--المعوقين،
and it's a lot more honest and respectful
وأكثر بكثير من صادقة ومحترمة
of the fragility of life.
هشاشة الحياة.
So my final takeaway for you is
ذلك بلدي الوجبات الجاهزة النهائي لك
that not only is the city good for the blind,
وهذا ليس فقط المدينة جيدة للمكفوفين،
but the city needs us.
ولكن المدينة بحاجة إلينا.
And I'm so sure of that that
وأنا متأكد من ذلك لأن هذا
I want to propose to you today
أريد أن اقترح عليكم اليوم
that the blind be taken as the prototypical city dwellers
أن تؤخذ المكفوفين كسكان مدينة تنميط
when imagining new and wonderful cities,
عندما تخيل المدن الجديدة والرائعة،
and not the people that are thought about
ولا الناس أن هي فكرت في
after the mold has already been cast.
تم الإدلاء بها بعد العفن بالفعل.
It's too late then.
أنها متأخرة جداً بعد ذلك.
So if you design a city with the blind in mind,
حتى إذا قمت بتصميم مدينة مع المكفوفين في الاعتبار،
you'll have a rich, walkable network of sidewalks
سيكون لديك شبكة غنية، والمشاة للارصفة
with a dense array of options and choices
مع مجموعة كثيفة من خيارات واختيارات
all available at the street level.
كل ما هو متاح على مستوى الشارع.
If you design a city with the blind in mind,
إذا قمت بتصميم مدينة مع المكفوفين في الاعتبار،
sidewalks will be predictable and will be generous.
الأرصفة سوف تكون قابلة للتنبؤ، وسوف تكون سخية.
The space between buildings will be well-balanced
المسافة بين المباني سوف تكون متوازنة
between people and cars.
بين الناس والسيارات.
In fact, cars, who needs them?
في الواقع، والسيارات، والذين بحاجة إليها؟
If you're blind, you don't drive. (Laughter)
إذا كنت أعمى، لا تدفع لك. (ضحك)
They don't like it when you drive. (Laughter)
أنهم لا يحبون عند قيادة السيارة. (ضحك)
If you design a city with the blind in mind,
إذا قمت بتصميم مدينة مع المكفوفين في الاعتبار،
you design a city with a robust,
يمكنك تصميم مدينة مع قوي،
accessible, well-connected mass transit system
نظام النقل الجماعي موجوداً، واتصال جيد
that connects all parts of the city
التي تربط جميع أجزاء من المدينة
and the region all around.
والمنطقة في جميع أنحاء.
If you design a city with the blind in mind,
إذا قمت بتصميم مدينة مع المكفوفين في الاعتبار،
there'll be jobs, lots of jobs.
سوف تكون هناك فرص عمل، الكثير من فرص العمل.
Blind people want to work too.
تريد المكفوفين العمل أيضا.
They want to earn a living.
أنهم يريدون كسب لقمة العيش.
So, in designing a city for the blind,
لذا، في تصميم مدينة للمكفوفين،
I hope you start to realize
وآمل البدء بتحقيق
that it actually would be a more inclusive,
أنه في الواقع سيكون أكثر شمولاً،
a more equitable, a more just city for all.
أكثر إنصافاً، وهي مدينة أكثر عدلاً للجميع.
And based on my prior sighted experience,
واستنادا إلى تجربتي المبصرين السابقة،
it sounds like a pretty cool city,
هذا يبدو وكأنه مدينة باردة جداً،
whether you're blind, whether you have a disability,
سواء كنت أعمى، عما إذا كانت لديك إعاقة،
or you haven't quite found yours yet.
أو أن لم تكن قد وجدت لك تماما حتى الآن.
So thank you.
حتى شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)